Menands Book Club; Records mss138
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Menands Book Club Records
1881-2009
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
mss138
0.67 cubic ft.
The majority of the Menands Book Club Records consists of meeting and treasurer notes and program schedules. There also is correspondence, club histories and an information packet of the village of Menands, NY Anniversary.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted with the exception of one folder noted below.
Acquisition Information
The Menands Book Club donated the records to the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives in 2011.
Biographical Sketch
The Menands Book Club was formed by Mrs. Edward A. Kelly, Mrs. Frank Dunn, and Mrs. Claude C. Nuckols about 1908. It was originally known as The Literary Club of Menands, NY. Members held informal meetings at a different member home each week.
As the literary club grew, members decided to create a more formal structure in 1910, including having club officers. The first president was Miss Alice M. Darbe. Along with assigning officers, members wrote a constitution and by-laws. The purpose of the Club as stated was to enlighten and fulfill intellectual needs. Meetings were now held every two weeks and the Club charged membership dues of 5 cents per member per meeting for attendees and 10 cents for those absent. Programs were printed for members with the meeting dates and topics. Members were required to share a reading on their assigned topic. The Club also selected books to reflect an overall theme in some years, including current events, women, New York State history, islands, far away places and American people and life.
The organization continued to evolve over time. The name changed to the Menands Book Club for the 1923-1924 program year. In 1954 and 2007 members revised the constitution and by-laws. The Club currently has about a dozen members and meets from September through June. Its meetings still cover a variety of topics.
Scope and Contents
The collection predominantly consists of paper-handouts and mini-booklets. In addition, there are some newspaper clippings and both ledger and composition notebooks to record meetings. There are guidebooks to the village of Menands anniversary celebrations in the collection as well. Please note there are gaps in the collection record in the 1940s and then again in the 1960s and 1970s, with the meeting program guides.
Series one contains administrative records. In the records there are meeting minutes and treasury information. Correspondence pertaining to administration of the Club and membership directories are also in this section. Series two contains materials related to programs and events. Within this series is correspondence regarding the history of the Club, program guides and newsclippings. There also are items retained by Club members that relate to the history of Menands, but pre-date the The Literary Club.
These records were located in the homes of members and members' families and collected by the Menands Book Club several years prior to the donation of materials to the University at Albany.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1 - Administration, 1908-2008, Undated
Series 2 - Programs and Events, 1881, 1898, 1910-2009, Undated
Both series are arranged alphabetically.
Women; Literature; Albany, New York; Book clubs (Discussion groups)--New York (State); Women--Societies and clubs.; Menands (N.Y.); Programs (documents); Clippings; Correspondence; Bylaws (administrative records); Schedules (time plans); Histories; Financial Records; Menands Book Club
- Administration, 1908-2008; Undated; 1; 0.43 cubic ft.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains correspondence pertaining to book club business, organizational history, laws, and membership information.
  - Account Statements-[RESTRICTED], 1985-1989 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 1)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Must consult archivist before viewing this material.
  - Club Laws, 1921; 2007 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1963-1965; 1968-1969 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1970-1977 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1980; 1982-1984; 1986; 1988-1989 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1991; 1994-1996; 1999 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 2001-2003; 2008 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 8)
  - Dues, 1981-1985 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 9)
  - History, 1974; 2007-2008; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 10)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1996-1999 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 11)
  - Meeting Minutes, 2000-2003 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 12)
  - Meeting Minutes, 2004-2007 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 13)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1998-2007 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 14)
  - Membership Cards for Red Cross, 1949-1951; 1955 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 15)
  - Membership Lists, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 16)
  - Receipts, 1964-1965; 1975; 1980; 1989; 1991 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 17)
  - Secretary and Treasurer Notes, 1908-1914 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 18)
  - Secretary and Treasurer Notes, 1948-1950 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 19)
  - Secretary and Treasurer Notes, 1948-1955 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 20)
  - Secretary and Treasurer Notes, 1955-1965 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 21)
  - Secretary and Treasurer Notes, 1965-1972 (Box 2 (1-Administration), Folder 1)
  - Secretary and Treasurer Notes, 1972-1982 (Box 2 (1-Administration), Folder 2)
  - Secretary and Treasurer Notes, 1982-1993 (Box 2 (1-Administration), Folder 3)
  - Secretary and Treasurer Notes, 1993-1996 (Box 2 (1-Administration), Folder 4)
- Programs and Events, 1881; 1898; 1910-2009; Undated; 2; .24 cu. ft.
  This series consists of calendars of events, newspaper clippings, histories of the village of Menands, meeting schedules and annual programs. Initially these programs were bound volumes listing such information as the meeting dates, book to be discussed, hostess for each meeting and presenters and topics. Eventually they became less elaborate and frequently were one sheet of paper featuring a typed meeting schedule.
  - Calendar of Events, 2007-2009 (Box 2 (2-Programs and Events), Folder 5)
  - Early Menands Historic Documents Retained by Club Members, 1881; 1898 (Box 2 (2-Programs and Events), Folder 6)
  - Menands Anniversary, 1974; 1979 (Box 2 (2-Programs and Events), Folder 7)
  - Menands History, Undated (Box 2 (2-Programs and Events), Folder 8)
  - News Clippings, 1984-2007 (Box 3 (2-Programs and Events), Folder 1)
  - News Clippings on Menands Book Club, 1931-1932 (Box 3 (2-Programs and Events), Folder 2)
  - Programs, 1910-1914 (Box 3 (2-Programs and Events), Folder 3)
  - Programs, 1914-1919 (Box 3 (2-Programs and Events), Folder 4)
  - Programs, 1919-1925 (Box 3 (2-Programs and Events), Folder 5)
  - Programs, 1926-1932 (Box 3 (2-Programs and Events), Folder 6)
  - Programs, 1932-1939 (Box 3 (2-Programs and Events), Folder 7)
  - Programs, 1944-1950 (Box 3 (2-Programs and Events), Folder 8)
  - Programs, 1950-1959 (Box 3 (2-Programs and Events), Folder 9)
  - Schedules, 1962-1963 (Box 3 (2-Programs and Events), Folder 10)
  - Schedules, 1969-1971 (Box 3 (2-Programs and Events), Folder 11)
  - Schedules, 1986-1990 (Box 3 (2-Programs and Events), Folder 12)
  - Schedules, 1992-2000 (Box 3 (2-Programs and Events), Folder 13)
  - Schedules, 2001-2007 (Box 3 (2-Programs and Events), Folder 14)